Guide to the Alfred Whitney Griswold Personal Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alfred Whitney Griswold personal papers
1914-1990
MS 255
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
28.5
The papers consist of student material from Hotchkiss and Yale College, including clippings of Griswold's column in the Yale Daily News and other publications; copies of articles and books; notes from courses at Yale Graduate School; lecture notes on political science and history; and student papers. Also included is correspondence of Alfred Whitney Griswold with family and friends, letters of congratulation on being elected president of Yale, and letters of condolences to Mrs. Griswold. Honorary degree hoods, memorabilia, calendars and date books, clippings and editorials upon his death, and a catalogue of the books in his library are also among the papers.
Griswold, Alfred Whitney, 1906-1963
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. A. Whitney Griswold, 1964, 1991, and 1996.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and three additions: I. Correspondence. II. Writings and other papers.
Biographical / Historical
Alfred Whitney Griswold was born in Morristown, New Jersey on October 27, 1906. He received a B.A. degree from Yale in 1929 and a Ph.D. in 1933. Griswold held various academic positions in history and government and international relations at Yale from 1933-1950. In 1950 he became president of Yale, an office he held until his death on April 19, 1963.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of student material from Hotchkiss and Yale College, including clippings of Griswold's column in the Yale Daily News and other publications; copies of articles and books; notes from courses at Yale Graduate School; lecture notes on political science and history; and student papers. Also included is correspondence of Alfred Whitney Griswold with family and friends, letters of congratulation on being elected president of Yale, and letters of condolences to Mrs. Griswold. Honorary degree hoods, memorabilia, calendars and date books, clippings and editorials upon his death, and a catalogue of the books in his library are also among the papers.
History -- Study and teaching; College presidents; Historians; Griswold, Alfred Whitney, 1906-1963; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University -- Presidents
- Correspondence, Series I
  - General
    - 1914-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
    - 1939-1943 (Box 2, Folder 15-24)
    - 1944-1949 (Box 3, Folder 25-33)
    - 1950-1956 November (Box 4, Folder 34-43)
    - 1956 December-1961 February 23 (Box 5, Folder 44-55)
    - 1961 February 24-1963 Jul, undated (Box 6, Folder 56-68)
  - Congratulations
    - A - H (Box 7, Folder 69-81)
    - H - S (Box 8, Folder 82-94)
    - S - Z (Box 9, Folder 95-99)
  - Condolences
    - A - F (Box 9, Folder 100-108)
    - F - R (Box 10, Folder 109-120)
    - R - Z (Box 11, Folder 121-127)
- Writings and other papers, Series II
  - Trip files, 1950-1963 (Box 12)
  - Calendars, 1950-1963 (Box 12)
  - Account books, 1943-1947 (Box 12)
  - Engagement books, 1939-1943; 1951 (Box 12)
  - Army Specialized Training Courses: World War II (Box 13)
  - Catalog cards: personal library (Box 14–15)
  - Manuscripts and essays Speeches, 1932-1936 (Box 16)
  - Farming and Democracy (Box 17–19)
  - Notes: History 36, Government 37, Int. Relations 103 and 1166 (Box 20)
  - Notes: Government 37, Int. Relations 103 and 1166 (Box 21)
  - Notes: History 36, American Studies (Box 22)
  - Notes:History 20a and 36b, American Studies 151 (Box 23)
  - Student papers
  - Yale Record, 1928-1929 (Box 24)
  - Hotchkiss Literary Magazine, 1922-1924 (Box 24)
  - English literature papers., 1925-1933 (Box 24)
  - American Gospel of Success: typed manuscript
  - Periodicals (Box 25)
  - Magazines (Box 25)
  - Manuscripts (Box 25)
  - Published material (Box 26)
  - The Far Eastern Policy of the United States (Box 27–28)
  - Photographs (Box 29)
  - An American History: annotated copy (Box 30)
  - Memorabilia (Box 31–35)
  - Miscellanea (Box 36)
  - Diaries, 1950-1962 (Box 37)
  - Ph.D. manuscript (Box 37)
  - Writings (Box 37)
  - Oversize (Box 38)
  - Diploma, University of Pennsylvania (Box 38)
- Additional material, 1927-1956, undated; Accession 1991-M-089; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1991 Jun
  Received from: Mary M. Griswold, 1991 Apr 26
  - Correspondence
    - Griswold, A. Whitney to Mary Morgan Brooks, 1927-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
    - Brooks, Mary Morgan to A. Whitney Griswold, 1928-1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
    - Griswold, Mary Morgan (Brooks) to A. Whitney Griswold, 1931-1947 (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
    - Griswold, A. Whitney to Mary Morgan (Brooks) Griswold, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Griswold, Alfred Whitney to A. Whitney and Mary Griswold, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence from others to A. Whitney Griswold and Mary Morgan (Brooks) Griswold, 1928-1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Griswold, A. Whitney to Harold Ely and Elsie (Whitney) Griswold (parents), 1938-1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Griswold, Elsie (Whitney) to A. Whitney Griswold, 1935-1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Griswold, Harold Ely to A. Whitney Griswold, 1935-1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Whitney, Alfred R. to A. Whitney Griswold, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Whitney, H. Leroy to A. Whitney Griswold, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Griswold, Elsie (Whitney) to Mary Morgan (Brooks) Griswold, 1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, 1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Additional material, 1940-1964, undated; Accession 1991-M-090; 1.50 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Received from: Mary M. Griswold, 1991 May 2
  - Correspondence
    - Griswold, A. Whitney, 1940, 1948-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Griswold, Mary (Brooks), 1950-1951, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Alfred Whitney Griswold - In Memoriam
      - Thank you notes, 1964-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-7)
      - Correspondence, preparations of volume, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Articles about A. Whitney Griswold, 1951-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Awards, 1954, 1959, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Book reviews, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Business cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Business Week article with accompanying photographs, 1954 May (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Funeral arrangements, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Griswold, A. Whitney: forty-seventh birthday party at the W. Johnstons, 1953 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hillhouse Avenue, interior decor of: photographs, 1950-1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - History 36, "Political Philosophy in the United States"
    - Assignments, 1948 September-1949 January (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Introduction, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - House and Garden photo spread with text of summer home at Martha's Vineyard, 1959 August (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lohmann, Carl A.: lines in honor of 25 years as Secretary of Yale, 1951 February (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Loose notes, 1950, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1944, 1950-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Photographs, 1950-1963 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Printed material, 1950-1955, 1961, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Programs and invitations, 1950-1964 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Speeches, 1950, 1957-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Travel notes, [1950-1953?] (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Watkins, Franklin: copies of portrait of A. Whitney Griswold, 1946, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Women's Affairs," guest program sponsored by the German Foreign Office, 1958 April 15 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Writings by A. Whitney Griswold, 1943, 1954, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Yale University Corporation entertaining: guest list, 1953-1964 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Yale University Presidency, announcement of: clippings, photographs, 1949, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Writings
    - Ph.D. thesis: carbon, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Thesis copyright, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - The Far Eastern Policy of the United States, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Farming and Democracy, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Essays on Education, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - In the University Tradition, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Liberal Education and the Democratic Ideal, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Farming and Democracy: correspondence, reviews, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Farming and Democracy: satirical version, compiler unknown, [1948] (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Obituaries and memoria (duplicate of scrapbook in box 26 of 1964 material), 1963 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Additional material, 1990; Accession 1996-M-105
  - Autobiography of Mary Brooks Griswold [typescript of chapters 3, 4, and 5], 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)